Let's move on to the next tag:
$ git checkout Example_3
$ git diff Example_2 Example_3
As you can see, the files have changed: README
and our script `calc`.
Let's take a look at `calc`:
$ cat calc
It looks more complicated -- let's analyze
the changes.
So the main idea behind the fixes is to read
the expression from stdin, not from the script
parameters, and modify it to avoid the Shell
matching mechanism.
OK.
On the third line, we define a FILE variable
with a unique name to store temporary data
for evaluating `expr`.
The uniqueness is guaranteed by a special
double dollar environment variable that indicates
the PID of the current process.
On the fifth line, we read the expression
from stdin into the EXPR variable.
We then edit it on the fly with the `sed`
stream editor.
By the `sed` command, we insert spaces between
numbers and signs of arithmetic operations,
we do the escaping with the slash character
before the asterisk and brackets.
Finally, before the expression, insert the
`expr` command and redirect the output from
`sed` to a temporary file defined at the beginning
of the script.
We then run our temporary script with `sh`,
getting the exit status from the special variable
"dollar question" into "EXIT_STATUS" variable,
deleting the temporary file, and exiting with
the parameters stored in "EXIT_STATUS".
We need such a complex construction because
`rm -rf` will return a success status regardless
of the result of evaluating the expression.
OK -- let's check our fixes:
$ ./calc
2*2
It works!
And we don't even need to insert spaces between
parts of our expression.
Let's check -- maybe something else was broken
by our corrections?
$ ./calc
1+2
5-7
-2
$ ./calc
6/3
7/3
$ ./calc
7%3
6/0
expr: division by zero
$ echo $?
So, looks good.
We got expected error -- the division by zero!
Of course, we can implement a simpler solution in the
sixth line with `sed` black magic just write:
echo $(($EXPR)) > $FILE
But we wrote a script that still works with
older shells that may not support such constructs,
and we also looked at how to use non-interactive
editing in scripts.