OK -- the next example
$ git checkout Example_4
It seems strange -- the commit and comment
are similar to the previous example.
Let's check diff:
$ git diff Example_3 Example_4
Oh yeah -- I was wrong, I placed the tag incorrectly
-- until the real changes!
This is actually a good reason to take a deeper
look into our repository to fix this.
First, let's move on to the next example:
$ git checkout Example_5
Ok -- seems differ.
Now let's look to log:
$ git log
commit f266a24128b1e363eddc073682aac89dd33a86a8
...
GUI
commit d6453c0c41548a55e3249ea8c3b788c71cb76f7e
...
Text UI.
commit d7f58c65c3e25269977538fdde0ac13d733fbf92
...
We see another commit between the previously
discussed commit and the GUI commit -- the
text interface.
Let's switch to it:
$ git checkout d6453c0c41548a55e3249ea8c3b788c71cb76f7e
...
Text UI.
OK. And what about diff?
$ git diff Example_3 d6453c0c41548a55e3249ea8c3b788c71cb76f7
So, OK -- changed README, Makefile and added new file.
$ ls
Makefile README.md calc calc_ui
`calc_ui` script is the user interface
for our simple command line calculator.
Let's take a look inside:
$ cat calc_ui
First, we see setting environment variables
for temporary files.
Then we define an `end` function in which
we delete the temporary files and exit the
program.
The main action in the program is an infinite
loop, in which we just call a `dialog` program
and then work with the results it returns.
What is it `dialog`?
To understand what it is, you first need to
install this program.
By this way on RH-like systems:
$ sudo yum insatll dialog
In Ubuntu, we have to install this program
as follows:
$ sudo apt install dialog
Now we just execute `dialog`:
$ dialog
We see a lengthy help that shows us which
parameters we should use to create various
interface forms.
For example:
$ dialog --yesno "To be or not to be?" 5 25
Make your choice and see the program exit
code:
$ echo $?
You will see zero if you choose 'yes' and
non-zero if 'no'.
As we understand it, this is a one-shot program
that shows us a uniform interface form and
returns some result that we can use in our
script.
In our UI we use the `--inputbox` form and
redirect the standard error from it to a temporary FILE1.
What does standard error have to do with our
command?
Hopefully we didn't expect any errors in a
line with our expression?
Yes, but the standard output of the `dialog`
program is already in use for drawing the
UI form.
As far as we understand, to draw such pretty
forms, a bunch of ESC sequences for your terminal
type are sent to standard output.
These sequences, generated by the `ncurses`
library, are retrieved from a terminal type
database according to the TTY environment
variable.
To remember this look at "Under the Hood
-- text terminals command sets" lecture.
Thus, if the dialog form ended with an error
exit code, it means that we clicked the "Cancel"
button and then calling the "end" function.
If we clicked OK, we perform the following
operation -- we send our ouput to our good
old `calc` script and redirect the output
and error output to separate files.
And then show a `dialog` form with the result
if the script completed successfully, and
an error form if we received an error.
So it looks good.
And this is an example of the KISS design
principle -- we developed a simple script
and just wrapped it with another simple script
that implements the UI.
But for the final preparation of our application
for work, we need to install our `calc` script
to the directory from the PATH environment
variable.
And for this, we added a corresponding rule
to the Makefile:
$ sudo make install
[sudo] password for liveuser:
install calc calc_ui /usr/local/bin
Now let's play with our user friendly calculator:
$ calc_ui
Great!