Speaking about the history of Linux we can
recall the well-known saying - we make our
inventions stand on the shoulders of giants.But
we must understand that many of these giants
have failed.
But such fails can be a good lesson for new
developers.
One such giant was the MULTICS project.
The development of Multics began in 1965 as
a research project by MIT, General Electric
and Bell Labs to create a time-sharing, multiprocessing
and multiuser interactive operating system.
After several years of development, the enthusiasm
of the developers decreased more and more
as the system became more and more complex
and the prospects for completion of development
became less and less.
Bell Labs pulled out of the project in 1969;
but some of the people who worked on it got
a lot of experience.
Among them were Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie
of Bell Labs, the inventors of the UNIX OS.
It's funny, but the history of Unix systems
is closely related to computer games.
It started in 1969 when Ken Thompson discovered
an old PDP-7 computer in a dark corner of
the lab and wanted to use it to play Space
Travel game.
There was little to do — an operating system
had to be written to run it.
And he did it -- at midnight on January 1,
1970, the Unix epoch began.
From this time on, all clocks in UNIX-like
systems count down the time, including your
mobile phone.
Originally it was a single-tasking OS written
in assembly language that was loaded from
paper tapes and called UNICS as opposed to
the complexity of MULTICS.
[Unix History Timeline](http://www.levenez.com/unix/)
And then the team of Ken Thompson and Dennis
Ritchie received a new DEC PDP11 computer
to develop a word processing system for the
Bell Labs patent department.
For the first three months the machine sat
in a corner, enumerating all the closed Knight's
tours on a 6×8 chess board — just because
the hard drive wasn't shipped with a super
new computer.
This time could be used to choose a programming
language, because it was a computer with a
completely new architecture and programs written
on PDP7 assembler was not useful for it.
And most interesting was the concept of another
project used in some R&D projects including
MULTICS -- BCPL.
It was a high-level programming language focused
on portability.
Most of this language was written in the language
itself, and only a small machine-dependent
part was written in assembly.
To support a new machine, only 1/5 of the
compiler code needed to be rewritten, which
usually took 2-5 man-months.
[Computer Languages History Timeline](http://www.levenez.com/lang/)
Thompson used the same concept when writing
his simplified successor to BCPL, language B.
This language was not very expressive and
effective on the PDP11.
In 1971, Ritchie started to improve B, which
resulted in creating a new language C.
In 1973, the UNIX kernel was refactored in C
language to follow the same concept of portability
-- most of the code was machine independent.
The system was distributed in source code
among universities for a nominal fee, which
served as an explosive growth in its popularity
in the 80s.
Almost all the developers of new computer
systems since this period have used UNIX as
the base platform for their new developments.
One of the most famous of these is the Berkeley
Software Distribution (BSD) developed at the
University of California, Berkeley and based on
Unix version 6 with its own copyleft license.
And most of the hardware vendors of the 1980s
used BSD as the base OS for their new computers.
UNIX was not a significant part of AT&T Bell
Laboratories' business, and it was not a problem
for them.
But in the 1980s Bell Labs split into several
companies as a result of an antitrust lawsuit
against AT&T.
The new UNIX System Laboratories company was
created and the new UNIX System V specification
was developed.
UNIX was the main business of this company,
and they were very aggressive in pushing the
new standard in the market.
And that has been the cause of UNIX wars against
non-commercial developers including BSD.
The commercialization of the UNIX system market
and the move to a closed development and distribution
model has led to an alternative movement -- the
GNU.
What is GNU?
You know, it's such an African animal.
But also it is a self-referential abbreviation
"GNU is
Not Unix".
Richard Stallman founded the project in 1978
at MIT.
The GNU project is a mass collaborative initiative
for the development of free software.
The first goal of this project was to develop
a set of programs similar to the standard
set of utilities in UNIX.
In 1991, a Finnish student Linus Torvalds
created his own operating system kernel, which
is compatible with the UNIX OS, called Linux.
As he said later, "Just for fun."
The Linux kernel, combined with the set of
utilities from the GNU project, served as
the basis for creating a complete operating
system, comparable in capabilities to commercial
UNIX systems, and usually even superior to
them.