Initially, when computer R&D projects were
mostly just university research, they were
open source and free of charge as a common
scientific research result.
In addition, scientists were very interested
in widespread dissemination of this result,
because their renommée, their reputation directly depended
on the prominence of their scientific work.
Commercialization has changed this world to
a closed and paid model.
Not completely closed, because standardization
is very important for government agencies
and corporate consumers to protect investments
and prevent vendor locking.
As a consequence, many open standards have
been created by committees and organizations:
POSIX, ANSI, ISO.
And openness was a serious weapon in business competition.
For example, some well-known companies.
including Bull, DEC, IBM, HP, Hitachi, Philips,
Siemens and others, created the
Open Software Foundation (OSF) to fight SUN and AT&T during
the so-called "Unix wars".
The POSIX subsystem (which was actually just
a description of UNIX-like systems standards)
was included in Microsoft Windows NT because
in the 1980s the US federal government required
compatibility with this open standard for
government contracts.
This openness is very important because we
get more compatible systems from different
vendors, ideally without undocumented features.
As a result, we have a computing infrastructure
with higher efficiency and lower cost of ownership.
But for some people, especially in the scientific
world, this is not enough.
And in 1985, Richard Stallman from MIT published
the GNU Manifesto where he announced the GNU
Project.
The main goal of this project was to create
a UNIX-like OS with a full set of UNIX utilities
from completely free software.
The Free Software Foundation (FSF) was formed
to support these activities.
But what is this freedom in the computer world
and how is it different from openness?
This difference is most accurately described
in licenses.
In the proprietary world, the most widely
used are so-called copyright licenses, which
usually restrict certain user rights.
Even with legal access to the source code,
the copyright holder can harass the consumer,
as we saw in the USL versus BSD or SCO versus
IBM lawsuits.
https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-software-for-freedom.en.html
In contrast, the free software world uses
copyleft licenses.
The most famous permissive licenses for free
software were published in the late 1980s.
Two of them, named BSD and MIT - the educational
institutions in which they were created - look
almost the same and give us the following
basic rights:
* The freedom to run the program as you wish,
for any purpose (freedom 0).
* The freedom to study how the program works,
and change it so it does your computing as
you wish (freedom 1).
Access to the source code is a precondition
for this.
* The freedom to redistribute copies so you
can help others (freedom 2).
* The freedom to distribute copies of your
modified versions to others (freedom 3).
By doing this you can give the whole community
a chance to benefit from your changes.
Access to the source code is a precondition
for this.
The most famous projects released under these licenses
are BSD Unix and the MIT X-Window graphics system.
Such licenses do not restrict the use of closed
derivative projects and their proprietarization.
To avoid this, the GNU General Public License
(GNU GPL or GPL) was developed.
One important limitation added to the fundamental
freedoms of this license (run, learn, share
and modify software) is the limitation for
closing.
Any derivative work must be distributed under
the same or equivalent license terms.
And the main difference between open-specification
software and truly free software is that we
actually have a de facto standard, not a de
jure standard.
In free and open source software, we have
working reference implementations that can
be used as a basis for future development
and cross-testing.
It's interesting, but this license does not
completely restrict the creation of proprietary
closed applications using GPL licensed software.
For example, the OS kernel or shared libraries,
simply because they are not included directly
in the proprietary application code.
We now have many free and open source licenses
approved by the Open Source Initiative.
Another challenge for the free and open world
is patent lawsuits.
For example, in 2007, Microsoft threatened to sue
Linux companies like Red Hat over patent violations.
To solve this problem GPLv3 license has been
created, along with some activities such as
the Open Invention Network (OIN), which have
a defensive patent pool and community of patent
non-aggression which enables freedom of action
in Linux.