$ git checkout Example_8
What is it "localize"?
The locale is the primary mechanism for supporting
the native languages in UNIX-like systems,
and we have a few strange abbreviations that
describe it: I18N, L10N, and even M17N.
What does this mean?
This means that English does not like long
words, but the terminology associated with
supporting native languages is too many letters.
Such as -- Multilingualization for application
software consisting of 17 letters between
"M" and "N" and abbreviated to M17N.
M17N is performed in 2 stages:
* Internationalization (18 letters between
"I" and "N" -- I18N): To make a software potentially
handle multiple locales.
* Localization (10 letters between "L" and
"N" -- L10N): To make a software handle an
specific locale.
OK.
Let's take a look at our current locale settings:
$ locale
As we can see, there are lot of environment
variables associated with this:
* LANG and LC_ALL -- General language setting.
These settings can be separated to:
* LC_CTYPE -- Controls the behavior of character
handling functions.
* LC_TIME -- Specifies date and time formats,
including month names, days of the week, and
common full and abbreviated representations.
* LC_MONETARY -- Specifies monetary formats,
including the currency symbol for the locale,
thousands separator, sign position, the number
of fractional digits, and so forth.
* LC_NUMERIC -- Specifies the decimal delimiter
(or radix character), the thousands separator,
and the grouping.
* LC_COLLATE -- Specifies a collation order
and regular expression definition for the
locale.
* LC_MESSAGES -- Specifies the language in
which the localized messages are written,
and affirmative and negative responses of
the locale ("yes" and "no" strings and expressions).
* LC_LTYPE -- Specifies the layout engine
that provides information about language rendering.
Language rendering (or text rendering) depends
on the shape and direction attributes of a
script.
In the C programming language, the locale
name C “specifies the minimal environment
for C translation” (C99 -- the
principle has been the same since at least
the 1980s).
As most operating systems are written in C,
especially the Unix-inspired ones where locales
are set through the LANG and LC_ environment
variables, C ends up being the name of a “safe”
locale everywhere.
On POSIX platforms such as Unix, Linux and
others, locale identifiers are defined by
ISO standard and consists from: `[language[_territory][.codeset][@modifier]]`.
For example, Australian English dialect
using the UTF-8 encoding
is en_AU.UTF-8.
As we can see, our application already has
l10n.
$ LANG=C calc_ui
$ LANG=en_US.UTF-8 calc_ui
As we can see, our application looks the same
in base C or American English locales.
In Russian we see the Russian title and buttons:
$ LANG=ru_RU.UTF-8 calc_ui
In Continental Simplified
$ LANG=zh_CN.UTF-8 calc_ui
and Traditional Taiwanese Chinese, we can
see different hieroglyphs sets on the title:
$ LANG=zh_TW.UTF-8 calc_ui
And for
the Arabic language, the title is written
from right to left:
$ LANG=ar_SY.UTF-8 calc_ui
Looks good, but this is just a basic localization
of the `zenity` utility used by `gdialog`.
We need to translate our text strings in the
program.
And for that we can use the standard `gettext`
machinery that was first implemented by Sun
Microsystems in 1993.
To work with this, we need a `gettext` utilities
set:
# yum install gettext
# apt install gettext
We have a utility `gettext` that translates
the text messages passed to it as arguments
according to the settings of the locale's
environment variables:
$ man gettext
As we can see, for this we just need to add
a call to the `gettext` utility in all places
where we used a text string as a parameter
to `gettext`, and insert the result of execution
into command lines by quoting the command
with "back apostrophes":
$ git diff Example_7 Example_8
Just three lines changed.
And now we can fetch the `gettext` strings from
the source using the `xgettext` utility:
$ make calc_ui.pot
xgettext -o calc_ui.pot -L Shell calc_ui
We got the portable object template file `calc_ui.pot`
that we will use as a basis for translation:
$ cat calc_ui.pot
For exmaple to Russian language:
$ msginit --locale=ru --input=calc_ui.pot
$ cat ru.po