$ git checkout Example_9
Ok.
Let's delete this file -- in the next example
we already have it:
$ rm calc_ui.pot
$ git checkout Example_9
As we can see, we just made a translation
into Russian of the corresponding PO file
and added installation steps to the Makefile.
Let's look at the PO file with Russian translation:
$ cat calc_ui-ru.po
First we have the metadata and then the pairs
of translation strings: `msgid` with the source
and `msgstr` with the translation.
This is not a best translation strategy because
some messages in one language
may have different meanings in other languages
in a different context.
And in larger software projects like Firefox
or Open/LibreOffice, other localization engines
have been used in which each line from the
user interface has its own unique identifier
and translation for each one.
And to simplify and unify the translation
process, they use such complex tools as specialized
editors with support for the translation memory
mechanism, for ex.
But `gettext` is widely used in the UNIX-like
world, and that's enough for our purposes.
Let's compile and install our translation
now:
$ sudo make install
As we can see, we compile our translation file
`calc_ui-ru.po` into `calc_ui-ru.mo`
and install the resulting binary localization
file into the LC_MESSAGES locale directory.
Let's check the result:
$ LANG=ru_RU.UTF-8 calc_ui
Great!
We have a calculator in Russian now!
Let's switch to English again:
$ LANG=en_US.UTF-8 calc_ui
In works.
For other languages, we still have the same
interface
because we didn't translate the messages for
them:
$ LANG=zh_CN.UTF-8 calc_ui
And maybe it's a good time to translate our
application into your favorite language...