Now it's time to start programming, Shell
programming.
As far as we understand, the shell works like
a normal program and has several options that
can be useful for debugging:
-v Print shell input lines as they are read.
-x Print commands and their arguments as they
are executed.
and finally "-c" and some STRING -- read and execute commands
from STRING after processing the options, then exit.
If your shell is Bash, you may get some help by such commands:
bash -c help
bash -c 'help set'
And, of course, you may read a manual page about your shell
Let's follow the good tradition started by
the classic book of Kernighan and Ritchie
"The C Programming Language" and write a standard
program "Hello World":
$ cat > hello
echo Hello word
^D
We complete the input with the EOF (Ctrl-D character).
Let's try to run now:
$ sh hello
Hello word
Good.
And now let's turn our script into a real
executable program:
$ chmod +x hello
$ ./hello
Hello word
Excellent!
Now we will talk about the arguments.
Let's look at our first positional parameter:
$ vi hello
echo Hello $1
$ ./hello
Hello
We called our script without parameters and
got nothing.
Let's add some parameter:
$ ./hello world
Hello world
But for several parameters it does not work:
$ ./hello world and universe
Hello world
Let's fix it:
$ vi hello
echo Hello $*
$ ./hello world and universe
Hello world and universe
Excellent!
As we can see, there is some difference between
different shells in the use of some special
variable names associated with script parameters.
We have different styles of parameters in Bourne-Shell, C-Shell.
The main advantage of the latest shells over the
classic Bourne Shell shell is the ability
to use more than 9 parameters.
Because in the Bourne Shell we have only one
digit for the parameter number.
In newer shells, we can use longer numbers
in square brackets.
A very important thing in the UNIX world is
the zero-numbered positional parameter.
Let's try to look at this:
$ vi hello
echo \$0: $0
$ ./hello
echo Hello $*
$0: ./hello
Hello
Zero parameter is just the name of the script.
And if you are familiar with the C language,
you probably know -- the same is in argv[0].
For what needs can such a parameter be used?
The most obvious answer seems to be to write
a nice error message about using of our script
We got some help about calling of our program.
But on UNIX-like systems we can use a very
interesting trick -- linking files.
Take a look at this super-nano-notebook.
It runs on OpenWRT, a Linux distribution that
you can find on your home internet router,
for example.
We have a fully functional set of Linux utilities,
but if we take a closer look, we can see that
all common UNIX utilities are just symbolic
links to a single "busybox" binary.
# ls -l /bin
Busybox just looks at the name it is running
under and performs the appropriate functions
from the busybox library.
This technique can reduce the memory consumption
of the embedded system.
Let's try to use this feature on our script:
$ vi hello
if [ $# -lt 1 ]
then
echo Usage: $0 who...
exit
fi
echo $0 $*!
$ ln -sf hello bye
$ /hello world
./hello world
$ ./bye bye
./bye bye
Voilà!