As we remember, the connection between stdout
and stderr looks like this:
prog 2>&1
What do these numbers mean?
To understand this, we need to know one more
thing -- file descriptors.
In Unix and related computer operating systems,
a file descriptor is an abstract indicator
(handle) used to access a file or other input/output
resource, such as a pipe or network socket.
File descriptors form part of the POSIX application
programming interface.
A file descriptor is a non-negative integer,
generally represented in the C programming
language as the type integer (negative values
being reserved to indicate "no value" or an
error condition).
Every started process on a UNIX-like system
has an associated open files table -- a table
of file descriptors.
Each Unix process (except perhaps a daemon)
should expect to have three standard POSIX
file descriptors, corresponding to the three
standard streams:
* 0 -- stdin
* 1 -- stdout
* 2 -- stderr
all the numbers are just positions in table
of
file descriptors.
On Linux, you can see this table for each
process in the `/proc` filesystem, for example
for the first process -- `init`:
$ sudo ls -l /proc/1/fd | less
As we can see, stdin and stdout are simply
redirected to `/dev/null` special device, and stderr does
not open.