The format of text data at first glance seems
to be quite simple and versatile -- in the
simplest case, we just have a set of bytes
encoded by the standard ASCII character table.
But if you look at the C language specification
of the `fopen` function in UNIX-like and MS
OSs, you will see an interesting difference.
On MS systems, you will find the translation
mode for newlines:
* `t` -- Open in text (translated) mode.
* `b` -- Open in binary (untranslated) mode;
translations involving carriage-return and
line feed characters are suppressed.
What does translation mean in this context?
In UNIX-like systems, there is no difference
between text and binary data.
To understand this, we need to go back to
the beginning -- the TTY interface.
Moreover -- to the good old typewriter.
The carriage return is the real part of the typewriter
that is used to return the paper to the far
right so that the printing mechanism is aligned
with the left side of the paper:
For electrically driven TTYs, a special ASCII
code does this job -- carriage return is defined
as 13 decimal (or hex 0D), '\r' in C-language
notation.
And another one is line feed -- 10 (or hexadecimal
0A), '\n' in C-language notation.
Despite the fact that we only pressed ENTER,
that is -- LF both UNIX and MS OS did it differently.
On UNIX, the device driver does this job -- if
we send it an LF, but needs a CR for the correct
line ending, the driver will just add it to
the device text stream.
Only the characters we typed on keyboard will
be placed in the text file -- only LF will
be at the end of the line.
But on MS systems this work is done while
working with text files.
If we work with this file type, the operating
system will automatically add CR to the text
data before LF.
This may cause some subtle errors, and we
have utilities such as `dos2unix` and `unix2dos`
to convert between these formats.
But in some cases, the problems plagued by
MS design cannot be solved in an easy way.
A story from real life: a long time ago at
the Physico-Technical Institute, our students,
while writing their master thesis, developed
an image processing system for processing
images from a holographic interferometer.
This system was designed according to the
KISS principle -- from very simple parts.
They have developed many different image filters
for cleaning the picture, for extracting interferometric
lines, for building a density map.
All of these simple programs were combined
by shell pipelines and simply sent the filtered
image data from one processing program to
another via standard I/O streams.
This approach allowed a fairly simple mechanism
for playing with set of filters and their
parameters and successfully writing master
thesis.
But one day Indian clients asked us for our
interferometer, but they needed a program
that would work on Windows.
Not a problem, us we know Microsoft OS'es
inherited from Unix the mechanism for redirecting
I/O streams and combining them through program
pipes.
We just recompiled the C source code on Windows
and ran our scripts as batch files.
And nothing works...
Why?
We are looking for a problem and we see -- the
OS works with standard I/O streams and pipelines
in text mode!
And inserts CR before the LF -- in the binary
image data.
And all the data is broken.
For solve the problem, we had to rewrite the
entire system in the standard Windows style
-- as a large monolithic application.