Core dump consists of the recorded state of
the working memory of a computer program at
a specific time, generally when the program
has crashed or otherwise terminated abnormally.
The name comes from "magnetic core memory",
the principal form of random access memory
from the 1950s to the 1970s.
The name has remained long after magnetic
core technology became obsolete.
Modern operating systems typically generate
a file containing an image of the memory belonging
to the crashed process, or the memory images
of parts of the address space related to that
process, along with other information such
as the values of processor registers, program
counter, system flags, and other information
useful for determining the root cause of the
crash.
These files can be viewed as text, printed,
or analysed with specialized tools such as
elfdump on Unix and Unix-like systems, objdump
and kdump on Linux.
Interesting use case for core-dump is initialization
of the
TeX typesetting system.
On old computers from the 70s it took a long
time to interpret TeX package macros, and
Donald Knuth, the creator of TeX, just developed
a mechanism that would core dump the `initex`
program after this interpretation.
And then it just needs to undump the core
dump by downloading directly to memory an
running to execution.
By this way we get the interpreted packages
immediately.
And the most common use of a core dump is
to view the debugger failure state, or for
example a frozen state, from which we core
dumping the application with C-\ keystroke
or the SIGQUIT signal.
This analysis can be very useful for embedded
systems where interactive debugging may not
be available.
By default, core dump is disabled on most
systems.
But you can use the `ulimit` command in `bash`:
$ ulimit -c
This means disabling the core dump.
And we may enable it:
$ ulimit -c unlimited
$ ulimit -c
unlimited
Also in Linux we have system wide config `/etc/security/limits.conf`
in which we may set hard and soft limits for
user and groups, including the limits for
core dump size:
$ cat /etc/security/limits.conf
$ man limits.conf