To understand what these hard and soft links
are, we need a brief introduction to the file
system structure of UNIX-like systems.
We have many different file systems on UNIX
world.
But the basic idea of all of them has remained
unchanged from the very beginning, since the
days of PDP7.
Typically, we can have
a boot block at the beginning of a device
or filesystem partition, then we have a so-called
superblock with filesystem metadata, and then
a data space with data blocks that make up
the files.
The superblock is a very "high level" metadata
structure for the filesystem, and is very
important for the filesystem.
And if the superblock of the partition is
damaged, the corresponding file system cannot
be mounted by the operating system.
Therefore, it is saved in multiple backups
for each file system on this drive.
The superblock includes some general information
about the file system and some tables, such
as a list of free data blocks, possibly a
list of bad blocks, and finally a list of
i-nodes.
Each i-node (or index-node) describes a separate
file.
It includes metadata related to the file,
such as ownership, access mode (read, write,
execute), and file type and size.
But i-node also includes a list of physical
blocks holding the files content.
The size of the blocks supporting a single
i-node is fixed and, when combined with the
data block size, determines the maximum file
size on that file system.
When you create some filesystems, you can
change the size of the i-node list and the
size of the data block, and use these options
to configure the filesystem to handle less
larger files or more smaller files.
And about directories -- actually it's just
a special kind of file
that contains a sequence of names
and their associated i-nodes.
We can have multiple directory entries associated
with one i-node and this is called a hard
link.
We can see this with the `ls` command with
`-i` (i-node) option:
$ touch 1
$ ls -l
total 0
-rwxrwxrwx 1 user user 0 Sep 4 20:02 1
$ ln 1 2
$ ls -i
50069589 1 50069589 2
As we can see, the 'a' and  'c' file related to the same i-node.
As we remember, changing any of the related
files changes the other file synchronously.
But this is interesting -- the mode change
also occurs synchronously for both files:
$ ls -l
total 0
-rw-rw-r-- 2 user user 0 Sep 4 20:02 1
-rw-rw-r-- 2 user user 0 Sep 4 20:02 2
$ chmod 777 2
$ ls -l
total 0
-rwxrwxrwx 2 user user 0 Sep 4 20:02 1
-rwxrwxrwx 2 user user 0 Sep 4 20:02 2
Just because the file's metadata is located
in the single i-node.
Also, the i-node has a file link counter.
In the UNIX API, we actually don't have something
like the `delete` system call -- just `unlink`.
And when we call the `rm` command, we just
doing `unlink` and decrement the link count.
Only when the link count reaches zero are
the data blocks associated with the file moved
to the free blocks list:
$ rm 2
$ ls -l
total 0
-rwxrwxrwx 1 user user 0 Sep 4 20:02 1
As we can see link counter now is one.
It looks good, but unfortunately we cannot
establish hard links between different file
systems, because it would be too difficult
to synchronize the metadata of these file
systems.
And for that, a soft or symbolic link was
designed in 4.2BSD.
How does a soft link look inside?
Let's look.
As we can see, this is just a special type
of file. We can see the length 1 instead
9 of the source file.
And this means only one thing -- a string
with the path to the linked file is simply
placed in this special file.
As a consequence, we have no restrictions
on linking between file systems.
But if we delete the original file, we will
lose access to it via this soft link.