Numeric octal mode for file permissions settings
may not seem very familiar to newbies, but
it can be very convenient if we understand
the principle.
As you probably know, our widely used from 0 to 9
numbering system is not the only one in the world.
It is base ten positional decimal system.
But we can use number systems with other bases.
For example, we know a binary system with
only two digits in the base -- 0 and 1.
Or the hexadecimal system with numbers from
0 to 9 and letters from A to F for the missing
6 numbers.
Or the Sumerian-Babylonian Sexagesimal number
system with sixty in the base and we still
use it in time measuring for example.
The decimal system has historically been most
widely used only because we have ten fingers
on our hands.
Binary representation of numbers is closest
to computing equipment.
And hexadecimal is the most compact -- each
byte is encoded with just two hexadecimal
numbers.
But what about octal numbering?
Oddly enough, but the octal numbering is closest
to the human perception of computer data.
Octal numerals can be made from binary numerals
by grouping consecutive binary digits into
groups of three (starting from the right).
We just need to sum the powers of two in the
corresponding positions:
0) two to the zero power equals one
1) two to the power of one equals two
2) and two to the power of two equals four
We just need to sum the powers of two in the
sequential positions of the binary triplet,
where we see one.
For example, all zeros mean zero, and all
ones mean one plus two plus four.
It's equal seven.
For file access rights, each three-bit group
of rights (read, write, execute for user,
group and others) can be represented by one
octal number.
For example:
* All permissions for the owner and completely
denied access for everyone else --
equals 700.
* Only owner and group can read and write,
and everyone else can only read. This is -- 664.
* The same with execution permissions for
all -- 775.