As we recall, we have the `passwd` utility
that any user can call to change the password.
But on the other hand, we did not have permissions
not only to write to the file in which the
password hashes are `/etc/shadow`, but also
to read.
How can a simple user change his password?
Actually on UNIX-like systems, there is a special
trick for this.
Let's take a look at the permissions of the
`passwd` utility:
$ ls -l /bin/passwd
At the place of execution permissions for
the owner, we see the letter 's' instead of
'x'.
Actually it is just a special kind of executable
permission that can be set for owner and group.
But when we run such files, our initial UID
or GID is changed to the ID of the file.
The process will start with a new effective
UID or GID equal to the file parameter.
And if we run the `passwd` command, we become
the` root` super-user while this program is running.
In this state, we can read and write to `/etc/shadow`.
We can set or unset suid and sgid on symbolic
mode using the 's' character.
In the binary mode
of the file, it looks like this:
$ stat -c "%a %A %n" /bin/passwd
4755 -rwsr-xr-x /bin/passwd
$ stat -c "%a %A %n" /bin/crontab
2755 -rwxr-sr-x /bin/crontab
Another question -- do you have any ideas
about the implementation of the, for example, `ps` utility?
Actually it seems pretty simple - we just
need to open the special file '/dev/mem',
read the current process table from it (from memory)
and pretty print it to stdout.
But for this we do not have permission to
read memory:
$ ls -l /dev/mem
crw-r----- 1 root kmem 1, 1 Sep 1 21:39 /dev/mem
And in the beginning the `ps` utility had
the `s` bit for such reading.
But what about today?
$ ls -l /bin/ps
-rwxr-xr-x 1 root root 137688 Feb 27 2020
/bin/ps
We don't have a setuid bit right now.
Why?
Because on most UNIX-like systems we have
a special `/proc` filesystem, which is just
a rabbit hole for the kernel.
It was implemented by Tom J. Killian for
UNIX 8th Edition in 1984.
All processes can be seen as subdirectories
in the `/proc` directory.
All processes can be thought of as subdirectories
in `/proc`, and we do not need the suid bit
to read process-related data from them.
Such a complex revision of the system kernel
brings us `ps` without the suid bit, which
is not so little.
Because every bit of 'suid' is a potential
hole in our security, and it is the daily
job of the sysadmin to look for new 's' bits
in executable files.
For automatic daily monitoring of such a task,
the `logwatch` utility may be useful.
Finally, the first bit of special permissions
is a sticky bit.
Let's take a look at the permissions for temporary
files directory -- `/tmp`:
$ ls -l /
drwxrwxrwt 25 root root 20480 Sep 6 21:23 tmp
So we can see the executable permissions for
the owner and group.
By the way, what does "executable" mean for
a directory?
Strange, but this permission means - you can
change to this directory, for example, with
the command `cd`.
And also we see permission 't' for directory
'/tmp'.
Generally `/tmp` directory is a publicly accessible
-- all users have all permissions to it.
Of course, they cannot modify files or directories
owned by others if we do not have such permissions,
but they can delete them, because everyone
has all the permissions to changing of that
directory.
And the file permission 1000 or 't' in character
mode means -- only the owner of something
can delete it in a directory with this bit.