A few words about devices and drivers. In
the classic Unix driver model, devices belong
to one of three categories: character devices,
block devices and network devices associated
driver types. Under Unix, drivers are code
units linked into the kernel that run in privileged
kernel mode. Generally, driver code runs on
behalf of a user-mode application. Access
to Unix drivers from user-mode applications
is provided via the file system. In other
words, devices appear to the application
as special device files that can be opened.
In the beginning, all drivers were built into
a monolithic kernel, and every change in a
set of devices required a rebuild of the kernel.
Then a mechanism for dynamically loading device
drivers was developed, which made reconfiguration
possible with support for dynamically changing
a set of devices. Nowadays, almost all modern
systems support this machinery -- we just
need to install a package with a new device
driver and this device will be supported by
the system immediately.
As we remember, we can access the device via
a pseudo-file in the '/dev' directory. And
these files will be special files:
$ ls -l /dev/null
crw-rw-rw-. 1 root root 1, 3 Aug 28 19:06
/dev/null
$ ls -l /dev/sda
brw-rw----. 1 root disk 8, 0 Aug 28 19:06
/dev/sda
We see this in the first character of the
permissions field:
* 'c' -- stands for character device
* and 'b' -- for block device.
We can work with both of them as with files,
but on block device a file system can be created.
What about file size? In place of the "size"
we see two strange numbers that have nothing
to do with, for example, the actual size of
the device. To understand the meaning of these
numbers, we must take a quick look at the
organization of the device subsystem in a
UNIX-like kernel.
From the very beginning, drivers in the UNIX
kernel were placed in two special tables,
`cdevsw` and `bdevsw` -- character and block
device switches. These tables have a separate
row for each device driver. And the first
number of two (the so-called "major number")
is just a position in this table. Each driver
places the initial entry points for standard
file functions in its own table row: `open`,
`close`, `read`, `write`, `seek` and everything
that did not fit into these functions - into
the `ioctl` (I/O control) function. To write
a new driver, you just need to implement such
functions for your device.
OK. But what about the second number -- the
so-called "minor number"?
Let's take a look at the '/dev' directory again:
$ ls -l /dev/zero
crw-rw-rw-. 1 root root 1, 5 Aug 28 19:06 /dev/zero
$ ls -l /dev/mem
crw-r-----. 1 root kmem 1, 1 Aug 28 19:06 /dev/mem
It looks interesting -- we have the same "major"
number for all devices '/dev/null', '/dev/zero'
and even '/dev/mem'. This means that they
are all handled by the same driver. And one
more thing:
$ ls -l /dev/sd*
As we can see, all hard disks with all partitions
are also handled by one driver. There is only
one difference between these files: the "minor"
number. And this is just a parameter that
is passed to the driver. By this minor number,
the driver understands which device we need
-- '/dev/null', '/dev/zero' or '/dev/mem'",
or what hard disk or partition we are working
with.
And in the old days, device special files in the
'/dev' directory were created by the `mknod`
utility in the MAKEDEV script with fixed major
and minor numbers. Today, all device files
are created automatically on the special device's
file system.
But the `mknod` utility can be useful in some
cases:
$ man mknod
As we can see, we can create special files
by choosing the device type: "c" for a character
and "b" for block devices. But we also have
a very special file type 'p' for so called
"named pipes". We can use it as shell's channels
for inter-process communications, but with entry-point into your file system hierarchy.
$ mknod /tmp/p p
$ cat > /tmp/p
^D
$ cat /tmp/p
qwe
Send the data from one process
and get the data, this data
from another process by
using this named pipe.
There are nothing the data really placed on the file system, on the real file.
It's just sending across the internal pipe's structures as common pipeline.