So, now let's discuss the backup and archiving.
Historically the first Unix archiver utility,
also known as `ar`, developed at 1971
in AT&T that maintains groups of files as
a single archive. Today, `ar` is generally
used only to create and update static library
files (which internally are simply archive
with object files, which compiled from source
files). That libraries the link editor or
linker uses. An implementation of `ar` is
included as one of the GNU Binutils.
But the most widely used archiving tools are
`tar` and `cpio`.
The `tar` is a "tape archiver" originally
developed in AT&T at end of 70s for storing
data on magnetic tapes. It saves many files
together into a single tape or disk archive,
and can restore individual files from the
archive:
Basic operations with a tar archive:
* 'c' -- create archive
* 't' -- list files in archive
* and 'x' -- extract files from archive
Useful options:
* 'v' -- verbose
* 'f' -- file or device file for archive.
"Dash" in this case used as name of file
means standard input or output.
The GNU version also supports compressing/decompressing
archives:
* -a, --auto-compress -- use archive suffix
to determine the compression program
* -Z, --compress, --uncompress -- the oldest
UNIX `compress` program, archive suffix
is `.tar.Z`
* -z, --gzip, --gunzip, --ungzip -- archive
suffix
is `.tar.gz` or just `.tgz`
* -j, --bzip2 -- archive suffix is `.tar.bz2`
or `.tbz2` or just `.tbz`
* -J, --xz --
archive suffix is `.tar.xz` or '.txz'
For standard classical UNIX `tar`, external compression/decompression
programs should be used by this way:
tar create archive to stdout, some files, gzip -c to some archive.
For looking in our compressed archive we may use such command.
And for getting some files from this archive:
The main problem with compressed archives is if
you have some corruption in the middle of the archive
file, you will lose all content from the tail.
Just because this format is focused on storing
on tape and all the metadata about files stored
sequentially, not in some central directory.
And if you want to improve the reliability
of your data, it makes sense to compress the
files separately and put them in an uncompressed
archive.
So, another widely used archiving tool is `cpio`:
Basic operations with it:
* -o|--create
* -t|--list: Print a table of contents of
the input.
* -i|--extract
* and also -p|--pass-through is so-called
copy-pass mode, `cpio` copies files from one
directory tree to another, combining the copy-out
and copy-in steps without actually using an
archive.
Unlike `tar`, which works with files, `cpio`
works with stdin/stdout.
This is good, but such an archive may contain
some special files that are not properly processed.
For example, you can get hard links split
across multiple files. And for real backup
in UNIX-like systems, special programs have
been developed that know about the internal
structure of the file system, for example:
* dump/restore -- ext2/3/4 filesystem backup/retore.
* and xfsdump/xfsrestore -- XFS filesystems backup/retore.
The main arguments are: the list of files and
directories for dump and '-f' for dump_file. But
we can also choose the "dump level", which
is just an integer. A level 0, full backup,
specified by -0 guarantees the entire file
system is copied. A level number above 0,
is so-called "incremental backup", tells `dump`
to copy all files new or modified since the
last dump of a lower level. The default level
is 0 (full backup).
And this makes it possible to implement various
"backup strategies". For example, you can
create a full backup at the end of the week
and then make incremental backups every day
of the week. Then at the end of the week for
new full backup, you can use the oldest backup
storage from the full backup pool. This way,
you will have weekly full backups for a specific
period and daily saved states in incremental
backups for a week or two.
And then you can extract the full dump or
individual files or directories from the saved
dump using the `restore` utility.
You can also do this interactively with `-i`
option.