Well. Now let's talk about installing software.
An initial set of software is installed
during system installation, and installed
software packages are updated by system
services when newer versions are published to the
distribution sites. But let's take a deeper look.
From the First Research Edition (November
3, 1971) in which the PDP-7 Unix was
rewritten on the PDP-11 processor, UNIX documented
the "User Maintained Programs" guidelines
by organizing third-party code as
so-called "packages" or "ports".
The two first Berkeley distributions introduced to
the user community third-party software packages
targeting Unix. Over the years packages
proliferated and got distributed,
initially through USENET newsgroups and
later over the Internet in the form of ports
to a specific operating system distributions.
The established filesystem directory
hierarchy, provided a template
for laying out the source code, the
documentation, and the manual pages. In addition,
the use of `make` utility provided a common way
for expressing compilation and deployment rules.
And now if we are talking about free
and open source, the most general way is
compiling from source. Many projects
just require downloading the source,
running the `configure` script, and
running `make install`. This command reads
an instruction from a file named "Makefile" and
installs the software into the target directory,
by default `/usr/local`. You can change this
and other settings during configuration.
Sounds good, but in most cases we may have
problems uninstalling and updating installed
software, because in most cases such actions may
not be so simple, and the rule of “uninstall”
mostly is not implemented in the Makefiles.
And to perform a complete set of actions
with the software, a special type of files called
software packages developed and also some software
were developed to manage them. They differ
on different systems and distributions.
BSD UNIX packaging has been extended
to the FreeBSD `ports` machinery,
which provides a mechanism for compiling
and installing third-party packages
and their dependencies. The
main package Linux utilities are
`rpm` (RH Package Manager) for RH-like systems and
`dpkg` for Debian-based distributions:
A package is just a file that you
can install, remove, and update.
But when we have many packages with a complex
system of dependencies between them, it
can be too difficult to handle the full set of
dependent packages during package manipulation.
To solve this problem, so-called "repositories"
have been developed, which collect many packages,
resolve dependencies between them and put
information about this in metadata files.
Such repositories are hosted on the servers
of the respective projects, and we
can access them via the Internet.
The main tools for working with repositories are:
* `yum` -- Yellowdog Updater Modified for
RPM repositories,
now replaced with `dnf` package manager.
* and
`apt` -- package manager for
Debian-based repositories.
As we can see, using these tools, we can perform
the same actions as with `rpm` and `dpkg`:
install, remove
and update packages
with dependencies. We can also
get information about packages
and package groups in the
repositories, get a list of
packages, search for packages by name
or by files included in the package.
Also may be useful `yumdownloader` -- program
for downloading RPMs from Yum repositories.
You can find descriptions of the repositories in:
* `/etc/yum.repos.d/` directory in RH-like
systems
* and
`/etc/apt/sources.list` --
in Debian-based distributions
To find out about the correlation between
package-related programs, you can see the "Table
of equivalent commands for package management
on both Ubuntu/Debian and Red Hat/Fedora
systems".
Also our "Under the hood -- Devices and
drivers" lecture may be of interest
to you about device drivers handling.
OK. And many programming languages
and development frameworks
have their own package
systems and repositories like
CPAN,
PyPi,
NPM, etc. Also in recent years, forms of
product distribution such as static binaries,
docker containers, or pre-configured virtual
machines have become increasingly popular too.