And now we are ready to do some kind of development
project.
We already have a "hello world" application.
And now we will try to implement the next
traditional program for novice developers
-- a calculator.
As a result, we will get a network client-server
application with a graphical user interface
localized into Russian language.
We can find the code for this project on github.
Github and for example GitLab supports hosting for software
development and version control with Git.
Version control (also known as revision control,
source control, or source code management)
is a class of systems for managing changes
to computer programs, documents, large web
sites, or other collections of information.
Version control is a component of software
configuration management.
The first generation VCS were intended to
track changes for individual files and checked-out
files could only be edited locally by one
user at a time.
They were built on the assumption that all
users would log into the same shared Unix
host with their own accounts.
The second generation VCS introduced networking
which led to centralized repositories that
contained the 'official' versions of their
projects.
This was good progress, since it allowed multiple
users to checkout and work with the code at
the same time, but they would all be committing
back to the single point of failure -- the
central repository.
Furthermore, network access was required to
make commits.
The third generation is distributed VCS.
In distributed VCS, all copies of the repository
are created equal -- generally there is no
central copy of the repository.
This opens the path for commits, branches,
and merges to be created locally without network
access and pushed to other repositories as
needed.
There are many VCS systems developed and used
on UNIX-like systems: SCCS, RCS, CVS, SVN,
Mercurial, Bazzar, etc., and Git is now the
most popular.
Git is a distributed version-control system
for tracking changes in source code during
software development.
It was created by Linus Torvalds in 2005 for
development of the Linux kernel.
The basic tool for working with Git repositories
is the `git` utility.
First we have to `clone` our repository:
$ git clone https://github.com/itmo-infocom/calc_examples
$ ls calc_examples/
Ok - we now have our own local copy.
Let's go inside:
$ cd calc_examples/
Now let's take a look at the tags that indicate
different stages of development:
$ git tag
Example_1
...
Example_9
And let's move on to the initial stage now:
$ git checkout Example_1
$ ls
As we can see, most of the files have disappeared
and now we only have a README and a Makefile.
Let's take a look at the README:
$ cat README.md
and at the Makefile:
$ cat Makefile
A Makefile is a file containing a set of directives
used by a `make` utility -- build automation tool to
generate a target/goal.
`Make` is the oldest and most widely used
dependency-tracking tool for building software
projects.
It is used to build large projects such as
the Linux kernel with tens of millions of
source code lines.
Usually, using `make` is pretty simple: you
just run `make` with no arguments:
In this case, the utility tries to find a
`makefile` that starts with a lowercase letter
and then with a capital letter.
Usually the `Makefile` with an uppercase letter
is placed in the project, the lowercase version
is often used for some local changes while
testing and customizing the Makefile of an
upstream project.
The makefile format is pretty simple -- It's
just a lot of rules for building projects:
$ cat Makefile
In the first position we see the "target",
after the semicolon, dependencies can be placed,
which are just other targets.
Lines following the description of targets
and dependencies which start with a TAB character,
there are commands that must be executed to
complete this target.
If the dependencies are files, make checks
the modification times of those files and
recursively rebuilds those dependency targets.
The current Makefile just includes a few targets
for working with the Git repository.
The first will start by default.
If we want to run another target, we must
pass it as a parameter when running the `make`
utility.