Another important thing for your filesystem
is the availability of data space.
In case your file system is full, it's wise
to analyze disk usage.
On many systems some graphical disk analysis
program will run and you can detect problems
visually.
But we can also do this job using command
line tools that can help you automate some
of the admin tasks.
The main tool for reporting file system disk
space usage is the `df` utility.
The most useful option is the "-h, --human-readable"
for human readable print sizes in kilobytes,
megabytes, gigabytes, and so on.
For a more accurate analysis, you can use
the `du` utility to estimate the file space
usage of directories and files.
So, we can get the size of some directory:
And the most commonly used options are "-k",
which displays sizes in kilobytes, and "-x",
which means that it will scan only this file
system and skip directories on other file
systems which may be mounted on sub-directories
of this directory.
Let's take a look at an example of using the
command line tools to find the largest directories
and files:
We examine the directory '/tmp', perform a
numeric sorting of the sizes of directories
and files, and redirect the result to the
viewer `less` for analysis.
And after finding the largest files and directories,
we can clean up our file system and before
this archive and back up some data.
The easiest way is to simply copy using the
`cp -a` command to some external drive, or
using `scp -rC` or `rsync -avz` to a remote
host.
Also, using the `cp` or` scp` commands, you
can just copy any partition or the entire
disk, because for us they are just files.
But a more efficient way to do this is with
the `dd` (disk dump) command:
$ man dd
By default, it just copies stdin to stdout,
perhaps with some re-coding if we ask.
But the most interesting options for us are:
'if' -- input file, 'of' -- output file, 'bs'
-- block size, 'count', 'seek' and 'skip'.
With a combination of these options, we can
select the input and output files, choose
the block size to increase speed of I/O, the
number of blocks we want to copy, and seek/skip
on output/input.
Thus, we can cut and paste any fragment from
one file or device to another.
Also we can use
the `od` (octal dump) command to low-level
view of a file or device in different formats.
For example -- let's look to our hard drive:
# od -bc /dev/sda1 | less