In addition to the "dollar" sign, which was
used to retrieve a value from a variable by
name, we have seen some other special characters
earlier: "space" and "tab" as word separators,
"hash" as a line comment.
We also have many other special characters.
"Newline" and "semicolon" are command separators.
The "ampersand" can also look like a command
separator.
But if you use this sign, the command written
before it will run in the background (that
is, asynchronously as a separate process),
so the next command does not wait for completion.
"Double quote"d string means partial quoting.
This disables the interpretation of word separator
characters within STRING - the entire string
with spaces appears as one parameter to the
command.
"Single quote"d string interpreted as a full
quoting.
Such quoting preserves all special characters
within STRING.
This is a stronger form of quoting than double
quoting.
"Backslash" is a quoting for single characters.
The "backquotes" indicates command substitution.
This construct makes the output of the command
available as part of the command line.
For example to assign to a variable.
In POSIX-compliant environments, another form
of command ("dollar" and "round brackets")
can be used.
And in the special characters of the shell,
we can see some of the characters that we
will see in the regular expressions.
They are used to compose a query
to find text data.
It is a very important part of the UNIX culture,
borrowed by many programming languages to
form such search patterns.
These are "asterisk" and a "question" signs.
"Asterisk" used when a filename is expected.
It matches any filename except those starting
with a "dot" (or any part of a filename, except
the initial "dot").
"Question" symbol used when a filename is
expected, it matches any single character.
The set of characters in "square brackets"
means -- any of this set.
The same with an "exclamation" sign --
none of this set.